Guide to the Mary Russell Mitford Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Mary Russell Mitford collection
1822-1854
GEN MSS 32
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.2
(1 box)
The collection includes professional correspondence regarding Mitford's book "Our Village" and other writings, personal correspondence, and manuscripts of poems and dramatic works. Correspondents include W. C. Bennett, Benjamin Robert Haydon, Thomas Noon Talfourd, William Morgan Kinsey, Abraham John Valpy, and Julia Rattray Waddington.
Mitford, Mary Russell, 1787-1855
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources as indicated on the individual folders. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to the English writer Mary Russell Mitford (1787-1855), which the library has acquired from various sources.
The collection includes professional correspondence regarding Mitford's book Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery and other writings, personal correspondence, and manuscripts of poems and dramatic works. Correspondents include W. C. Bennett, Benjamin Robert Haydon, William Morgan Kinsey, Thomas Noon Talfourd, Abraham John Valpy, and Julia Rattray Waddington.
Authors, English -- Archives; Bennett, W. C. (William Cox), 1820-1895; Haydon, Benjamin Robert, 1786-1846; Kinsey, William Morgan, 1788-1851; Mitford, Mary Russell, 1787-1855; Talfourd, Thomas Noon, 1795-1854; Valpy, Abraham John, 1787-1854; Waddington, Julia Rattray
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1822-1854; Series I; 0.16; (30 folders)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically by recipient.
  - ALS to Mr. Bassett, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Discussing Our Village and other literary matters
  - 15 ALS and ANS to W. C. Bennett, 1848-54 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Bound in one volume; accompanied by ALS to Benjamin R. Haydon (1829 Apr 22), 3 portraits of Mary Russell Mitford, illustration from her book, Our Village, a portrait of William Mitford, ANS of John Mitford to his bookseller, Mr. Macphersson (1837 Jan 9)
  - ALS to W. C. Bennett, [Swallowfield], 1851 Dec 22 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - ALS to Mrs. Blandy, Three Mile Cross, near Reading (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Accompanied by an engraved portrait of Miss Mitford
  - Envelope addressed to Charles Boner, Portland Place, London, 1847 Jul 14 (Box 1, Folder 4a)
    Note in Mitford's hand on verso concerning Caroline Clive ("V.")
  - ALS to Rupert Clarke, [Reading], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - ALS to Mr. [Glennig?], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Written in the third person
  - ALS to John Hooke Greene, 1831 May (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Concluding lines only
  - ALS to Mrs. [Samuel Carter] Hall, Three Mile Cross, [1828 Feb 14?] (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Concerning plans for a children's story
  - ALS to Mrs. Hanmer, [1835?] (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Removed from: Our Village by Mary Russell Mitford (London, 1856)
  - ALS to Mrs. Holland, 1838 Mar 27 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 2 ALS to John Hughes, Reading, [1850], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - ALS to John Hughes, Newbury, 1850 Mar 28 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Enclosed are copies of two poems, "A Thames Voyage" and "The Pauper's Drive," by Roden Berkeley Wriothesley Noel
  - 2 ALS to John Hughes, Reading, 1851-52 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Accompanied by holograph transcription of a poem, "On Lending a Punch Bowl"
  - ALS to Mrs. Hughes, Three Mile Cross, near Reading, 1850 Jul 4 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - ALS to Mrs. Charles Kingsley, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - ALS to William Morgan Kinsey, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Accompanied by engraved portrait of Mary Russell Mitford
  - ALS in third person to James Kirkby, Three Mile Cross, near Reading, 1845 [Oct 31] (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 3 ALS and 1 letter written in the hand of her mother to Thomas Noon Talfourd, Three Mile Cross, 1822-37 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Accompanied by reproductions of an engraved portrait of Miss Mitford and an engraved picture of Mitford castle in Northumberland
  - ALS to Charles Tilt, 1837 [Jul 21] (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Accompanied by a photomechanical reproduction of a portrait of Mary Russell Mitford
  - ALS to Abraham Valpy, Three Mile Cross, near Reading, 1828 Oct 31 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - AL to Julia Rattray Waddington, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Concerning Waddington's book The Monk and the Married Man
  - AL to B. W., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - ALS to unidentified recipient, Three Mile Cross, near Reading, 1831 Jan 4 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Acknowledges a gift of "your Ladyship's portrait"
  - AL (fragment) to unidentified recipient, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - ALS to unidentified recipient, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - ALS to an unidentified recipient [Reading], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 2 ALS to unidentified recipients, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    One concerning the title of a book, and the other also on literary matters
  - ALS fragment, to an unidentified recipient, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Draft of a letter from an unidentified correspondent, Worthing, 1841 Dec 1 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- WRITINGS, 1831-1847; Series II; 0.04; (7 folders)
  Series II, Writings, is arranged alphabetically by title or first line.
  - "Fair May! Beneath Thy Feet The Grass is Set," autograph poem, signed, 1847 Jul 23 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - "Fair May! Beneath Thy Feet the Grass is Set," autograph poem, signed, 1847 Jul 30 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - "Inez de Castro", 1831 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    "Extract from Inez de Castro, an unpublished Tragedy," autograph manuscript, 1 page, addressed to David Russell, London
  - "Reply," autograph poem, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - "Song," autograph poem, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Inscribed to a Miss Brooks
  - "Sweet is the balmy evening hour," autograph poem, signed, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - "Thy sorrowing hand to many a plant[?] hath given," autograph poem (Box 1, Folder 36)